Guide to the Richard Slotkin Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Richard Slotkin papers
1959-2005
1969-1999
WA MSS S-2716
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
35.1
(59 boxes)
This collection documents the research and writing of Richard Slotkin chiefly related to his historical studies and works of historical fiction, 1959-2005. Material includes his research notes, his typed drafts, and proofs of works. Other material includes Slotkin's course notes and papers from his doctoral work at Brown University.
Slotkin, Richard, 1942-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Richard S. Slotkin, 1983-2005. Gift of Joseph W. Reed, 1991. Gift of Joseph W. Reed and Kit Reed, 1993.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 41 and 59 (computer disks): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services.
Richard S. Slotkin (born 1942)
American historian and novelist Richard Slotkin received his Bachelor of Arts from Brooklyn College in 1963, and his doctorate from Brown University in 1967. He received an honorary Master of Arts in Art Education from Wesleyan University in 1976. In 1966, Slotkin began his academic career at Wesleyan University, where he remained until 2009, when he retired and became the Olin Professor of English and American Studies Emeritus at Wesleyan.
Slotkin's historical works comprise a trilogy on the mythology of the American West: Regeneration Through Violence: The Mythology of the American Frontier, 1600-1860 (1973); The Fatal Environment: The Myth of the Frontier in the Age of Industrialization, 1800-1890 (1985); and Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America (1992). His other historical studies include Lost Battalions: The Great War and the Crisis of American Nationality (2005) and No Quarter: The Battle of the Crater, 1864 (2009). Slotkin also edited So Dreadfull a Judgment: Puritan Responses to King Philip's War, 1675-1677 (1978), with James K. Folsom, and provided notes and an introduction to a Penguin Books edition (1986) of The Last of the Mohicans, by James Fenimore Cooper. His works of historical fiction consist of The Crater (1980), The Return of Henry Starr (1988), and Abe: A Novel of the Young Lincoln (2000).
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the research methodologies and writing techniques of Richard Slotkin chiefly related to his historical studies and works of historical fiction, 1959-2005. Material includes his research notes, his typed drafts, and proofs of works. Other material includes Slotkin's course notes and papers from his doctoral work at Brown University.
Slotkin's historical studies documented in the collection include: Regeneration Through Violence: The Mythology of the American Frontier, 1600-1860 (1973); The Fatal Environment: The Myth of the Frontier in the Age of Industrialization, 1800-1890 (1985); Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America (1992); Lost Battalions: The Great War and the Crisis of American Nationality (2005); and No Quarter: The Battle of the Crater, 1864 (2009), as well as an article, "Equalizers: The Six-Gun Mystique in American Culture."
Slotkin's historical fiction documented in the collection include The Return of Henry Starr (1988) and Abe: A Novel of the Young Lincoln (2000).
Slotkin's unpublished works documented in the collection include a biography of George Armstrong Custer and a novel based on Oglala Indian leader Crazy Horse.
Arrangement
Organized by acquisition into nine groupings: November 1983 Acquisition, March 1985 Acquisition, November 1985 Acquisition, September 1986 Acquisition, June 1992 and February 1993 Acquisitions, January 1993 Acquisition, February 1993 Acquisition, July 1999 Acquisition, September 2005 Acquisition.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time.
Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with and/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
African American soldiers -- History -- 20th Century; American literature -- 19th century -- History and criticism; American literature -- History and criticism; Authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; Frontier and pioneer life -- United States; Frontier and pioneer life -- United States -- Historiography; Frontier and pioneer life -- West (U.S.); Frontier and pioneer life in literature; Frontier thesis; Historians -- 20th Century; King Philip's War, 1675-1676; Little Bighorn, Battle of the, Mont., 1876 -- Historiography; Minorities -- United States; Mythology in literature; National characteristics, American; Petersburg Crater, Battle of, Va., 1864; Popular culture -- United States -- History -- 20th Century; Puritans -- New England; Western films -- Political aspects; World War, 1914-1918 -- Regimental histories -- United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Participation, African American; New England -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; West (U.S.) -- History; Born digital; Crazy Horse, approximately 1842-1877; Custer, George A. (George Armstrong), 1839-1876; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865 -- Childhood and youth -- Fiction; Slotkin, Richard, 1942-; Starr, Henry, 1873-1921 -- Fiction; United States. Army -- African American troops -- History -- 20th Century; United States. Army ( Recruiting, enlistment, etc.); United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 369th -- History
- November 1983 Acquisition, 1.2; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 13.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Richard S. Slotkin, 1983.
  - Regeneration Through Violence: The Mythology of the American Frontier, 1600-1860.
    - Typescript drafts with manuscript corrections, 15 (Box 1)
    - Typescript drafts with manuscript corrections, 6 (Box 2)
    - Page proofs with manuscript corrections, 9 (Box 2)
    - Page proofs with manuscript corrections, 13 (Box 3)
- March 1985 Acquisition, 0.2; (1 box)
  Contains typescript drafts and copies of Slotkin's writings.
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 44.
  Gift of Joseph W. Reed, 1985.
  - Typescript drafts with manuscript corrections, 1982-1985, undated; 4 (Box 4)
    Includes typescript drafts and xerographic copies of chapters "The Last Stand as Ideological Objects, Myth and Genre, Form and Content" and "To the Last Man" from The Fatal Environment: The Myth of the Frontier in the Age of Industrialization, 1800-1890, as well as a draft of The Return of Henry Starr.
- November 1985 Acquisition, 2; (5 boxes)
  Contains the final typescripts and galley proofs of The Fatal Environment: The Myth of the Frontier in the Age of Industrialization, 1800-1890, and the final typescript of No Quarter: The Battle of the Crater, 1864.
  Former call numbers: Uncat WA MS 50 and Uncat WA MS 51.
  Gift of Richard S. Slotkin, 1985.
  - The Fatal Environment: The Myth of the Frontier in the Age of Industrialization, 1800-1890
    - Final typescript with corrections and annotations, 13 (Box 5)
    - Final typescript with corrections and annotations, 13 (Box 6)
    - Galley proofs, 2 (Box 7)
  - No Quarter: The Battle of the Crater, 1864
    - Final typescript with author corrections and annotations, 21 (Box 8)
    - Final typescript with author corrections and annotations, 24 (Box 9)
- September 1986 Acquisition, 4.3; (6 boxes)
  Includes typescript of The Fatal Environment: The Myth of the Frontier in the Age of Industrialization, 1800-1890, along with unpublished biography of George Armstrong Custer, with research materials, and an unpublished novel based on Oglala Indian leader Crazy Horse (Thašúŋke Witkó). Also includes microfilm relating to the unpublished Custer biography.
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 64.
  Gift of Richard S. Slotkin, 1986.
  - Typescript drafts with corrections, 35 (Box 10)
    Includes original typescript of The Fatal Environment: The Myth of the Frontier in the Age of Industrialization, 1800-1890, and drafts of chapters of Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America.
  - Typescript drafts with corrections, 1975-1982; 20 (Box 11)
    Includes typescripts of "The Man with Grey Eyes," an unpublished novel based on Crazy Horse (Thašúŋke Witkó) and an unpublished biography of George Armstrong Custer, as well as typescripts of lectures about Custer.
  - Research materials related to George Armstrong Custer, 1975-1977; 19 (Box 12)
    Includes notebooks and photocopies of newspapers.
  - Microfilm related to George Armstrong Custer (Box 13)
    Microfilm reproduces the George and Elizabeth B. Custer Papers in the Eastern Montana College Library (Billings, Montana), as well as a George A. Custer, My Life on the Plains, or, Personal Experiences with Indians (1874).
  - Microfilm related to George Armstrong Custer (Box 14)
  - Index cards with notes related to George Armstrong Custer (Box 15)
- June 1992 and February 1993 Acquisitions, 0.2; (1 box)
  Includes an uncorrected advance proof of Volume II of Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, as well as a corrected typescript draft of "Equalizers: The Six-Gun Mystique in American Culture."
  Former call number: Uncat WA MSS File.
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America: uncorrected advance proof of Volume II, 1992 (Box 16)
    Gift of Richard S. Slotkin, 1993.
  - "Equalizers: The Six-Gun Mystique in American Culture": typescript draft with corrections (Box 16)
    Gift of Richard S. Slotkin, 1992
    General note
    Published in Guns, Crime, and Punishment, edited by Bernard Harcourt (New York: NYU Press 2003).
- January 1993 Acquisition, 13.3; (24 boxes)
  Contains drafts, research files, and galley proofs of Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, The Return of Henry Starr drafts, as well as index cards with notes for The Fatal Environment: The Myth of the Frontier in the Age of Industrialization, 1800-1890.
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 160.
  - Index cards with notes related to the research and composition of The Fatal Environment: The Myth of the Frontier in the Age of Industrialization, 1800-1890., 1981-1982 (Box 17)
  - The Return of Henry Starr, 1976-1977; 21 (Box 18)
    Includes typescript drafts, notebooks, and unproduced screenplay. Also includes drafts of the first three scenes composed for the novel, titled "Howitt", "Used to Be", and "Magic City", as well as a final draft of "Disco" by Barry Armyan Bernstein.
  - The Return of Henry Starr, 1976-1977; 7 (Box 19)
    Includes typescript drafts, handwritten notes, and notebooks.
  - The Return of Henry Starr, 1976-1977; 3 (Box 20)
    Includes typescript drafts and a notebook.
  - The Return of Henry Starr, 15 (Box 21)
    Includes revised typescript drafts with minor revisions.
  - The Return of Henry Starr, 11 (Box 22)
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 1977-1982; 16 (Box 23)
    Includes early typescript drafts of ideas and chapters.
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 1977-1982; 7 (Box 24)
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 1989-1990; 19 (Box 25)
    Includes typescript first draft with corrections.
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 1989-1990; 15 (Box 26)
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 1989-1990; 5 (Box 27)
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 1989-1990; 2 (Box 28)
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 6 (Box 29)
    Includes the first revised draft of the submitted manuscript.
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 7 (Box 30)
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 5 (Box 31)
    Includes edited manuscripts by Don Fehr of Atheneum.
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 3 (Box 32)
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 11 (Box 33)
    Includes drafts and notes relating to the conclusion.
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 6 (Box 34)
    Includes material related to the composition of individual chapters, such as drafts of the organization and revision plans of the work, library research notes, and outlines for books and projects.
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 2 (Box 35)
    Includes four spiral bound notebooks containing outlines and research notes.
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 1969-1980, undated; 20 (Box 36)
    Includes material relevant to the movie sections of the book, such as notebooks and file folders containing notes on films Slotkin viewed.
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 1973-1984 (Box 37)
    Contains index cards with notes on movie genres.
  - Research files for Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America
    - Abstract proposal for Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America addressed to Atheneum publishers. (Box 38)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 38)
    - "MS Theory Movies": notes and early drafts for work on film genre, 5 (Box 38)
    - "Vnam West": early drafts on Vietnam War era Westerns, 3 (Box 38)
    - Lecture on Buffalo Bill's Wild West Show, 4 (Box 38)
    - "Mythic L-scape": lectures and articles related to chapters on the "Calvary Westerns", 5 (Box 38)
    - "Detectives": lecture on hard-boiled detective, 3 (Box 38)
    - "Deadwood Dick": dime novel material (Box 38)
    - "J. James": photocopies of research related to dime novels about Jesse Woodson James (Box 38)
    - "Lowrys": notes and newspaper photocopies relating to the gang of Henry Berry Lowrie, 2 (Box 38)
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 7 (Box 39)
    Contains the final edited manuscript and galley proofs.
  - Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 5 (Box 40)
  - Computer media, 2
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Gunfighter Nation 1st Draft GFINTRO.DOC TR.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0001; 1 (Box 41)
      Box 41: Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Gunfighter Nation, 1st BBWW.DOC MOB.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0002; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation 1st Draft VIR.DOC DIX.DOC FST.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0003; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation 1st Draft FORM.DOC GFMV1.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0004; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation 1st Draft GFMV2.DOC GFMV3.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0005; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation 1st Draft WAR.DOC CLASSIC.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0006; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation 1st Draft GF.DOC GFGB.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0007; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation 1st Draft JFK.DOC JFK2.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0008; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation, 1st Draft WB.DOC WB2.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0009; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation 1st Draft CONC.DOC DIME.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0010; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation 2nd Draft 2GFI.DOC 2TR.DOC 2BBWW.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0011; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation, 2nd Draft 2MOB.DOC 2DIME.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0012; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation, 2nd Draft 2VIR.DOC 2DIX.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0013; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation, 2nd Draft 2FORM.DOC 2HART.Doc 2DEP.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0014; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation, 2nd Draft 2REN.DOC 2WAR.DOC 2GF.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0015; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation, 2nd Draft 2CLAS.DOC 2GFGB.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0016; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation, 2nd Draft 2JFK.DOC 2JFK2.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0017; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation 2nd Draft 2WB.DOC 2WB2.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0018; 1 (Box 41)
    - Gunfighter Nation 2nd Draft CONC2.DOC 2CONC.DOC 2GFTI.DOC, 1993-wa-0126-b-0019; 1 (Box 41)
- February 1993 Acquisition, 0.2; (1 box)
  Contains one page proof of Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America.
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 159.
  Gift of Joseph W. Reed and Kit Reed, 1993.
  - Uncorrected advance proof of Gunfighter Nation: The Myth of the Frontier in Twentieth-Century America, 1992 (Box 42)
- July 1999 Acquisition, 9.5; (12 boxes)
  Contains drafts and notes of Abe: A Novel of the Young Lincoln, The Return of Henry Starr, No Quarter: The Battle of the Crater, 1864, and other writings, and Slotkin's college papers and notes.
  Former call number: Uncat WA MS 251.
  Gift of Richard S. Slotkin, 1999.
  - Abe: A Novel of the Young Lincoln, 1993-1999; 8 (Box 43)
    Contains the final submitted draft of the novel. Also includes correspondence with Slotkin's editors and agents, working notes, essays, and maps.
  - The Return of Henry Starr: early draft, 10 (Box 43)
  - The Return of Henry Starr: early draft, 3 (Box 44)
  - Abe: A Novel of the Young Lincoln: early drafts and notes, 12 (Box 45)
  - "Invisible Girl": first draft, 14 (Box 46)
  - No Quarter: The Battle of the Crater, 1864, 10 (Box 47)
    Includes edited manuscript drafts, correspondence with publishers, research notes, and master proofs.
  - Graduate papers and notes
    - American Studies: notes and syllabus (Box 48)
    - Briton Hammon: research material (Box 48)
    - Chaucer, Milton, Dante, and English History (Box 48)
    - College notebooks, 3 (Box 48)
    - Communitarianism and Education in the U.S., 1962-1963 (Box 48)
    - English/French/FLIP 174: course material (Box 48)
    - English 277 paper (Box 48)
    - "Eugenics": research material (Box 48)
    - Faulkner (Box 48)
    - Fiction (Box 48)
    - "The Ideal State": essay by Slotkin, 1959 (Box 48)
    - "Intel. Hist. II" (Box 48)
    - Judaism, 1965 (Box 48)
    - Modern American Literature - notes (Box 48)
    - National Purpose and Peace Corps (Box 48)
    - Peace Corps (Box 48)
    - Poetry: Slotkin's drafts and notebooks, 3 (Box 48)
    - "Stowe-Postwar" (Box 48)
    - World Literature and Utopia (Box 48)
    - Unidentified (Box 48)
    - African-American (Box 49)
    - Boone and Church (Box 49)
    - Colonial literature (Box 49)
    - American literature - modern - papers (Box 50)
    - American literature between wars (Box 50)
    - American Renaissance (Box 50)
    - American Studies (Box 50)
    - "The Antagonists" (Box 50)
    - "Bradley, Eliot and 'The Grand Harmony'": paper, 1961 January 8 (Box 50)
    - College notebooks, 2 (Box 50)
    - Colonial literature materials, 2 (Box 50)
    - Draft: "Jackson" (Box 50)
    - Draft: "Review of Theodore L. Gross, The Heroic Ideal in American Literature " (Box 50)
    - English 101 material (Box 50)
    - English 242 lectures (Box 50)
    - English notebook (Box 50)
    - Faulkner article (Box 50)
    - Intellectual history notes (Box 50)
    - Lecture notes (Box 50)
    - "The Negro Image in the Liberal Northeast": paper, 1964 January 6 (Box 50)
    - Newspaper articles (Box 50)
    - Romantics course (Box 50)
    - Walt Whitman (Box 50)
    - Unidentified, 2 (Box 50)
  - Abe: A Novel of the Young Lincoln
    Includes an abandoned section related to Lincoln's adventures in the Black Hawk War.
    - Revised version of first submitted draft; basis of the second submitted draft., 4 (Box 51)
    - Second draft; basis of first submission., 18 (Box 51)
  - Abe: A Novel of the Young Lincoln: second draft, 10 (Box 52)
  - Abe: A Novel of the Young Lincoln, 11 (Box 53)
    Contains first, second, and third drafts with revisions.
  - Abe: A Novel of the Young Lincoln, 5 (Box 54)
- September 2005 Acquisition, 4.2; (5 boxes)
  Contains drafts and source material relating to the book Lost Battalions: The Great War and the Crisis of American Nationality.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 814.
  Gift of Richard S. Slotkin, 2005.
  - Source material, 10 (Box 55)
  - Typescript drafts with corrections, 5 (Box 55)
  - Typescript drafts with corrections, 7 (Box 56)
  - Source material, 8 (Box 56)
  - Source material, 11 (Box 57)
  - Typescript drafts with corrections, 4 (Box 57)
  - Typescript drafts, 9 (Box 58)
  - Computer media
    - SLOTKIN "LOST BATTALIONS", 2005; 2005-wa-0926-g-0001; 1 (Box 59)
      Contains source materials and drafts not on paper.